<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The copie of a letter to the Right Honourable the Earle of Leycester, Lieutenant generall of all her Maiesties forces in the vnited Prouinces of the lowe Countreys written before, but deliuered at his returne from thence: vvith a report of certeine petitions and declarations made to the Queenes Maiestie at two seuerall times, from all the lordes and commons lately assembled in Parliament. And her Maiesties answeres thereunto by her selfe deliuered, though not expressed by the reporter with such grace and life, as the same were vttered by her Maiestie.</title>
            <author>Salisbury, Robert Cecil, Earl of, 1563-1612.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1586</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19619</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109079</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844729</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844729</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9567</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19619)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9567)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 212:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The copie of a letter to the Right Honourable the Earle of Leycester, Lieutenant generall of all her Maiesties forces in the vnited Prouinces of the lowe Countreys written before, but deliuered at his returne from thence: vvith a report of certeine petitions and declarations made to the Queenes Maiestie at two seuerall times, from all the lordes and commons lately assembled in Parliament. And her Maiesties answeres thereunto by her selfe deliuered, though not expressed by the reporter with such grace and life, as the same were vttered by her Maiestie.</title>
                  <author>Salisbury, Robert Cecil, Earl of, 1563-1612.</author>
                  <author>Crompton, Richard, fl. 1573-1599, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Elizabeth I, Queen of England, 1533-1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 3, [1], 4-32, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1586.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The letter signed: R.C., i.e. Robert Cecil, Earl of Salisbury.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Richard Crompton.</note>
                  <note>Regarding the proposed execution of Mary, Queen of Scots.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>From p. 4 on, even numbers are on the rectos.</note>
                  <note>The letter comes in two versions; A3r, text starts (1) "Albeit with earnest" or (2) "Albeit the earnest".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mary, --  Queen of Scots, 1542-1587.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Elizabeth, 1558-1603 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:9567:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9567:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE COPIE OF A LET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Earle of LEYCESTER, Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant generall of all her Maieſties forces in the vnited Prouinces of the lowe Countreys, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before, but deliuered at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from thence:</p>
            <p>With a report of certeine petitions and declarations made to the QVEENES Maieſtie at two ſeuerall times, from all the Lordes and Commons lately aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament.</p>
            <p>And her Maieſties anſweres thereunto by her ſelfe deliuered, though not expreſsed by the repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with ſuch grace and life, as the ſame were vttered by her Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie. 1586.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:9567:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:9567:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Earle of Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbeit with earneſt deſire of my hart (right honourable my very good Lord) I haue alwayes ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to do your Lordſhip ſome acceptable ſeruice, for the honour you firſt vouchſafed me from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my cradel, and after confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with the fauourable opinion wherewith you haue alwayes countenaunced me euer ſince, euen thus farre onward on my daies, which alſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with my yeres hath increaſed faſter then mine abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to performe, being croſſed in nothing more deepely, then when I was letted by the ouermuch tendring of me by my parents, to attend your Lordſhip in your late voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and honourable expedition into the Lowe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: yet haue I bene euer ſince moſt ſtudious to obſerue and apprehende ſome good occaſion, or fitte oportunitie, to teſtifie the duetifull reuerence I beare to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: wherein if hitherto I haue beene ſlacke in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance during your abſence, it hath proceeded of the care I had, not to entertaine your Lordſhip with matter either friuolous or vulgar: though thinges of that nature might beſt become my condition, and well agree with my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</p>
            <p>In which cogitation it came to my minde, that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the ſpeaches deliuered by the Queenes moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:9567:3"/>Maieſtie in a late and weightie cauſe dealt in this Parliament, in anſwere to the petitions preſented to hir Maieſtie the 12 &amp; 24. of Nouember at Richmond by the Lord Chauncelour and Speaker, reſpectiuely, in the name and behalfe of both Eſtates, accompanied with diuers of either ſort, would doubtleſſe bee a thing to your L. moſt gratefull, as one euer pleaſed iuſtly to admire the rare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of her mind, and approoued Iudgement, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, according to your Eſtate &amp; place, deſeruedly, your L. hath beene vſually acquainted: as alſo worthie of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal monument and euerlaſting memorie, for as much as on the ſodaine they were deliuered by her ſelfe, for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of a matter propounded, debated, reſolued, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted, with great labour and premeditation, of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, graueſt, wiſeſt, and moſt choiſe perſons of the whole Realme. Whereof although I haue but ſle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derly purtraied the lineaments, without expreſſing to life the external or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of her Royall ſpeach, accompanied with all Princely and gracefull accomplementes: yet doubt I not but your Lordſhip will eaſily finde her inward vertues, whereof it is impoſsible for mee to make the leaſt adum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration.</p>
            <p>And becauſe in the dayly expectation of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips returne, I reſted vncertaine how theſe might come ſafely to your Lordſhips hands: I did therefore aduiſe to haue this my letter with the included copies to be ready to attend your firſt arriuall, in gratulation of the ſafetie thereof, which hath bene long deſired. Wherein, as I ſtriue to performe a particular duetie to your Lordſhip, ſo truſt I you will haue that honourable conſideration, that in the communication thereof with others, there growe not any preiudice to me for my preſumption, in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenturing to be a reporter of that, which in the deliuerie wrought ſo great aſtoniſhment to all the hearers, as it exceeded the fulnes of euery mans expectation: and therefore, without ſome fauourable conſtruction of mine
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:9567:3"/>attempt, I might incurre great blame by my ſlender ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of report, ſo to haue blemiſhed the excellencie of her Maieſties ſpeaches, whereof I humbly beſeech your Lordſhip to haue fauourable regard. Thus referring them to your Lordſhips diſpoſition, and my ſelfe to your fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable protection, I humbly take my leaue. 25. Nouemb. 1586.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humbly in all duetie to commaund. <hi>R. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="summary_of_speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:9567:4"/>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:9567:4"/>
            <head>THE BRIEFE OF THE Lorde CHANCELLERS firſt ſpeach, at the time when he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered her moſt excellent MAIESTIE a petition in writing, for, and in the name of the Lordes and Commons: Which ſpeaches were of more length then here are by me collected: but ſure I am, the ſubſtance thereof is here truely expreſſed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the Lordes and Commons hauing of long time to their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable griefe, found, by howe many practiſes the Scottiſh Queene had compaſsed the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of her Highnes most Royall perſon (in whoſe ſafetie next vnder God they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged their chiefe felicitie to conſiſt) thereby not onely to bereaue them of the ſincere and true Religion in this Realme profeſſed and eſtabliſhed, but to bring backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine this noble Realme into the thraldome of Romiſh tyrannie, and to ouerthrowe the happie estate thereof: wherein, although her Highneſſe of her abundant gratious naturall clemencie &amp; Princely magnanimitie, hath either lightly paſsed them ouer, or with no ſmall indulgence tolerated, notwithstanding the often and earnest instances of her Nobilitie and Commons in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9567:5"/>ſudry Parliaments heretofore: and further hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected her from the violent purſuite of her owne people: ſhe yet, as a perſon obdurate in malice (as it appeares,) continued her former practiſes, as had bene lately mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested by certaine wicked conſpiracies plotted by one <hi>Anthonie Babington,</hi> and diuers deſperate perſons, that had combined and confederated themſelues by vowe and oth in a moſt horrible enterpriſe, by murther to take away the life of her Maiestie: wherein the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Q. did not only aduiſe them, but alſo direct, comfort, and abbette the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with perſwaſion, counſel, promiſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, &amp; earneſt obtestation. Whereupon, her Maieſtie at the earnest requeſt of ſuch as tendered the ſafetie of her royall perſon and the quiet of the Realme, did direct Commiſsion vnder the great Seale to ſundrie Lords and others of her Maieſties priuie Counſel, and a great nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Lordes of Parliament, of the greateſt and moſt ancient degree, aſsiſted with ſome of the principall Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Realme, to heare, examine and determine the ſame, according to a Statute in that behalfe made in the xxvij. yeere of her reigne. Who, to the nomber of 36. hauing attended the execution of the ſaid Commiſsion, and diuers daies and times heard the allegations againſt the ſaid Scottiſh Queene in her owne preſence and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, (ſhe being permitted to ſay what ſhee woulde in her owne excuſe,) did with one aſſent, finde her cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable both in priuitie and conſent to the ſaide crimes obiected, and alſo in compaſsing the Queenes Maieſties death. Which ſentence, by her owne directions vpon the hearing of the prooues and proceſſe in Parliament, was iudged to haue beene moſt honourable and iuſt, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:9567:5"/>thereupon they all beſeech hir Maieſty, that foraſmuch as the ſaid Queene of Scots, was the very ground and onely ſubiect, whereupon ſuch daungerous practiſes and complots had bene founded, againſt hir Maieſties most Royall perſon and the Eſtate of this Realme for theſe many yeeres, to the ouerthrowe of ſundrie of the Nobilitie of the land, and danger of Chriſtian religion, and that they coulde ſee no hope of her deſiſting, and her adherents, hut that ſtill her Maieſties ſafetie muſt bee hazarded, and ſtand to the euent of the like miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous diſcoueries:</p>
            <p>Therefore, as moſt humble and inſtant ſuppliants, they did vpon their knees at her moſt gratious feete, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech and requeſt in moſt earneſt maner, that aſwell for the continuance of Gods Religion, the quiet of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, preſeruation of her perſon, and defence of them and their poſterities, it woulde pleaſe hir Highneſſe to take order, that the ſaide ſentence might be publiſhed, and ſuch further direction giuen, as was requiſite in this ſo weightie a cauſe, according to the purport and intent of the ſaid Statute. Wherin, if her Maieſtie (pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing her wonted clemencie) ſhould nowe be remiſse, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the imminent danger to hir perſon, ſhe might by the ſtay thereof, procure the heauie diſpleaſure of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, as by ſundry ſeuere examples of his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in the ſacred Scriptures, doth appeare. And ſo he deliuered, to her Maiesties owne handes, the petition in writing, which he ſaid, had bene with great delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration aſſented vnto, by all the whole Parliament.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="reasons">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:9567:6"/>
            <head>A SHORT EXTRACT OF ſuch reaſons, as were deliuered in ſpeach by Maſter Sergeant Puckering, Speaker of the Lower Houſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie in her Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence Chamber at Richmond, the xii. of Nouember 1586. in the xxviii. yeere of her Reigne, containing diuers apparant and imminent dangers, that may grow to her Maieſties moſt Royal perſon, and to her Realme from the Scottiſh Queene and her Adherents, if reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die be not prouided.</head>
            <p>¶ Firſt, touching the danger of her Maieſties perſon.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Oth this Scottiſh Queene and her fauourers, doe thinke her to haue right, not to ſucceed but to enioy your Crowne in poſſeſsion: and therefore as ſhe is a most impacient competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, ſo will ſhee not ſpare any meanes whatſoeuer, that may bereaue vs of your Maieſtie, the onely impediment that ſhe enioyeth not her deſire.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Shee is obdurate in malice againſt your royall perſon, notwithſtanding you haue ſhewed her all fauour and mercie, as well inpreſeruing her kingdome, as ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing her life, and ſaluing her honour. And therefore there is no place for mercie, ſince there is no hope that ſhee will deſiſt from moſt wicked attempts: the rather for that her malice appeareth ſuch, that ſhee maketh (as it were) her teſtament of the ſame, to be executed after her death, and appoynteth her executors to performe it.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:9567:6"/>
            <p n="3">3 Shee boldly and openly profeſſed it lawfull for her to mooue inuaſion vpon you. And therefore, as of inuaſion victorie may enſue, and of victorie, the death of the vanquiſhed: ſo did ſhee thereby not obſcurely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraie, that ſhee thought it lawfull for her to deſtroie your ſacred perſon.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Shee thinkes it not onely lawfull, but honourable alſo and meritorious to take your life from you, as being alreadie depriued of your Crowne by the excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holie father. And therefore it is like ſhee will (as hitherto ſhe hath done) continually ſeeke it by what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer meanes.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That ſhee is greedie of your Maieſties death, and preferreth it before her owne life and ſafetie: for in her direction to one of her late Complices, ſhe aduiſed (vnder couert termes) that whatſoeuer ſhould become of her, that tragicall execution ſhould be performed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">The danger of the overthrow of the true Religion.</note>1 IT most perillous to ſpare her, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually hath ſought the ouerthrow and ſuppreſsion of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, infected with Poperie from her tender youth, and being after that a Confederate in that <hi>Holy league</hi> when ſhe came to age, and euer ſince a profeſſed enemie against the trueth.</p>
            <p n="2">2 She resteth wholly vpon Popiſh hopes to deliuer and aduance her, and is thereby ſo deuoted to that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, that aſwell for ſatisfaction of others, as for fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of her owne humor, ſhe will ſupplant the Goſpell, where, and whenſoeuer ſhe may: which euill is ſo much the greater, and the more to be auoyded, as that it ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:9567:7"/>the very ſoule, and will ſpread it ſelfe not onely ouer England and Scotland, but alſo into thoſe partes beyond the Seas, where the Goſpell of God is mainteined, the which cannot but be exceedingly weakened, by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of this noble Ilande.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">The perill of the ſtate of the Realme.</note>1 AS the Lydians ſaide, <hi>Vnum Regem agnoſcunt Lydi, duos autem tolerare non poſſunt:</hi> So wee ſay, <hi>Vnicam Reginam Elizabetham agnoſcunt Angli, duas autem tolerare non poſſunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 As ſhe hath already by her allurements brought to destruction moe Noble men and their houſes, together with a greater multitude of the Commons of this Realme, during her being here, then ſhe ſhould haue bin able to doe, if ſhe had bene in poſseſsion of her owne Crowne, and armed in the fielde against vs: ſo will ſhe ſtill be continuall cauſe of the like ſpoyle, to the greater loſse &amp; perill of this Estate: And therefore this Realme neither can, nor may endure her.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Againe, ſhe is the onely hope of all diſcontented ſubiects, ſhe is the foundation whereon all the euill di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed do builde, ſhe is the roote from whence all rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and trecheries do ſpring: And therefore whilest this hope lasteth, this foundation ſtandeth, and this roote liueth, they will reteine heart, and ſet on foote whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer their deuiſes againſt the Realme, which otherwiſe will fall away, die and come to nothing.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Mercie now in this caſe towards her, would in the ende proue crueltie againſt vs all, <hi>Nam eſt quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam crudelis miſericordia,</hi> and therefore to ſpare her, is to ſpill vs.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:9567:7"/>
            <p n="5">5 Beſides this, it will exceedingly grieue and in a manner deadly wound the hearts of all the good Subiects of your land, if they ſhall ſee a conſpiracie ſo horrible not condingly puniſhed.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Thouſands of your Maieſties moſt liege and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Subiectes, of all ſorts and degrees, that in a tender zeale of your Maieſties ſafetie, haue moſt willingly both by open ſubſcription and ſolemne vowe, entred into a firme and loyall aſſociation, and haue thereby proteſted to purſue vnto the death, by all forcible and poſsible meanes, ſuch as ſhe is by iuſt ſentence nowe found to be: can neither diſcharge their loue, nor well ſaue their othes, if your Maieſtie ſhall keepe her aliue: of which burden your Maieſties Subiects are moſt deſirous to bee relieued, as the ſame may be, if iuſtice be done.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Laſtly, your Maieſties moſt louing &amp; dutiful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons doubt not, but that as your Maieſtie is duely exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in reading the Booke of God, ſo it will pleaſe you to call to your princely remembrance, how fearefull the examples of Gods vengeance bee, that are there to bee founde againſt King <hi>Saul</hi> for ſparing King <hi>Agag,</hi> and againſt King <hi>Achab</hi> for ſauing the life of <hi>Bena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dad:</hi> both which were by the iuſt iudgement of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of their kingdoms, for ſparing thoſe wicked Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whome God had deliuered into their handes, of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be ſlaine by them, as by the miniſters of his eternal and diuine Iustice: Wherein full wiſely <hi>Salomon</hi> proceeded to puniſhment, when hee tooke the life of his owne naturall and elder brother <hi>Adonias,</hi> for the only intention of a marriage, that gaue ſuſpition of treaſon againſt him.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:9567:8"/>
            <p>Herein we your Maieſties moſt louing and obedient ſubiects, earneſtly depend vpon your princely reſolution, which we aſſure our ſelues ſhall be to God moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and to vs no other, then the ſtate of your Regall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie may afford vs, and the approoued argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of your tender care for our ſafetie vnder your charge, dooth promiſe to our expectation</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:9567:8"/>
            <head>A REPORT OF HER MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties moſt gratious anſwere, deliuered by her ſelfe verbally, to the first petitions of the Lords and Commons, being the Estates of Parliament, in her Chamber of Preſence at Richmond, the xij. day of Nouember 1586. at the full almost of xxviij. yeeres of her Reigne: Whereof the Reporter requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth of all that were hearers, a fauourable interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his intent, becauſe he findeth that he can not expreſse the ſame anſwerable to the originall, which the learned call <hi>Prototypon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE bottomleſſe graces and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurable benefits beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me by the Almightie, are, and haue bene ſuch, as I muſt not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge them, but admire them, accounting them as well miracles as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, not ſo much in reſpect of his diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, with whome nothing is more common then to doe things rare and ſingular: as in regard of our weakeneſſe, who can not ſufficiently ſet foorth his wonderfull worker and graces, which to mee haue bene ſo many, ſo diuerſely folded and imbroydered one vpon another, as in no ſorte I am able to expreſſe them.</p>
            <p>And although there liueth not any, that may more iuſtly acknovvledge them ſelues infinitely bounde vnto God then I, whoſe life he hath mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly preſerued at ſundry times (beyonde my merite) from a multitude of perils and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9567:9"/>yet is not that the cauſe, for which I count my ſelfe the deeplyeſt bounde to giue him my humbleſt thankes, or to yeelde him greateſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognition: but this which I ſhall tell you hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which will deſerue the name of wonder, if rare things and ſeeldom ſeene be worthie of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt: Euen this it is, that as I came to the Crowne with the willing hearts of my ſubiects, ſo doe I now after xxviij. yeres Reigne, perceiue in you no diminution of good willes, which if happily I ſhould want, well might I breath, but neuer thinke I liued.</p>
            <p>And now, albeit I finde my life hath bene full dangerouſly ſought, &amp; death contriued by ſuch as no deſert procured: yet am I therein ſo cleare from malice (which hath the property to make men glad at the falles and faultes of their foes, and make them ſeeme to doe for other cauſes, when rancor is the ground) as I proteſt it is and hath bene my grieuous thought, that one, not different in ſexe, of like Eſtate, &amp; my neere kin, ſhoulde fall into ſo great a crime: yea, I had ſo litle purpoſe to purſue her with any colour of malice, that as it is not vnknowen to ſome of my Lordes here, (for nowe I will play the blabbe) I ſecretly wrote her a letter vpon the diſcouery of ſundry Treaſons, that if ſhe woulde confeſſe them, and priuately acknowledge them by her letters to my ſelfe, ſhee neuer ſhoulde neede be called for them into ſo publike queſtion. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did I it of minde to circumuent her: for then
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9567:9"/>I Knew as much as ſhe could confeſſe, and ſo did I write. And if euen yet, nowe that the matter is made but to appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, I thought ſhe truely would repent (as perhappes ſhe would eaſily appeare in outwarde ſhewe to doe) and that for her, none other would take the matter vpon them, or that we were but as tvvo milke maides vvith pailes vpon our armes, or that there vvere no more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendancie vpon vs, but mine ovvne life vvere onely in danger, &amp; not the vvhole Eſtate of your Religion and vvell doings, I proteſt (vvherein you may beleeue me, for though I may haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vices, I hope I haue not accuſtomed my tongue to be an inſtrument of vntrueth) I would moſt vvillingly pardon and remit this offence.</p>
            <p>Or if by my death, other nations and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes might truely ſay, that this Realme had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained an euerproſperous &amp; floriſhing eſtate: I vvould (I aſſure you) not deſire to liue, but glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giue my life, to the ende my death might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure you a better Prince.</p>
            <p>And for your ſakes it is, that I deſire to liue, to keepe you from a vvorſe. For as for me, I aſſure you, I finde no great cauſe I ſhould be fonde to liue: I take no ſuch pleaſure in it, that I ſhoulde much vviſh it, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaue ſuch terror in death, that I ſhould greatly feare it: and yet I ſay not, but if the ſtroke vvere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, perchance fleſh and blood vvould be moued vvith it, and ſeeke to ſhunne it.</p>
            <p>I haue had good experience and tryall of this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9567:10"/>vvorld: I know what it is to be a ſubiect, what to be a Soueraigne: vvhat to haue good neighbors, and ſometime meete euill willers. I haue founde treaſon in truſt, ſeene great benefits litle regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp; in ſtead of gratefulnes, courſes of purpoſe to croſſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe former remembrances, preſent feeling, and future expectation of euils, I ſay, haue made me thinke, <hi>An euill, is much the better, the leſſe while it endureth:</hi> and ſo, them happieſt, that are ſooneſt hence: &amp; taught me to beare with a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter minde theſe treaſons, then is common to my ſexe: yea, with a better heart perhaps, then is in ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Which I hope you wil not meerly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute to my ſimplicitie or want of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, but rather, that I thus conceiued, that had their purpoſes taken effect, I ſhould not haue found the blow, before I had felt it: and, though my pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill ſhould haue bene great, my paine ſhoulde haue bene but ſmal &amp; ſhort: wherein, as I would be loth to dye ſo bloody a death, ſo doubt I not, but God would haue giuen me grace to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for ſuch an euent, chance when it ſhall, which I referre to his good pleaſure.</p>
            <p>And now, as touching their treaſons and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies, together with the contriuer of them, I will not ſo preiudicate my ſelfe and this my Realme, as to ſay or thinke, that I might not, without the laſt Statute, by the ancient lawes of this land, haue proceeded againſt her, which was not made particularly to preiudice her: though
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9567:10"/>perhaps it might then be ſuſpected, in reſpect of the diſpoſition of ſuch as depend that way.</p>
            <p>It was ſo farre from being intended to intrap her, that it was rather an admonition to warne the danger thereof: but ſith it is made, and in the force of a Lawe, I thought good, in that which might concerne her, to proceede according thereunto, rather then by courſe of common Law: wherein, if you the Iudges haue not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me, or that the books you brought me were not falſe (which God forbid) I might as iuſtly haue tried her, by the ancient Lawes of the land.</p>
            <p>But you Lawyers are ſo nice in ſifting and skanning euery woorde and letter, that many times you ſtand more vpon forme then matter, vpon ſillables then ſence of the Lawe. For in the ſtrictnes and exact folowing of common forme, ſhee muſt haue beene indited in Stafford Shire, haue holden vp her hand at the Barre, and bene tried by a Iurie: A proper courſe forſooth, to deale in that manner with one of her Eſtate. I thought it better therfore, for auoiding of theſe and more abſurdities, to commit the cauſe to the inquiſition of a good nomber of the greateſt and moſt noble perſonages of this Realme, of the Iudges and others of good accompt, whoſe ſentence I muſt approoue: And all litle enough: For we Princes, I tel you, are ſet on ſtages, in the ſight and viewe of all the world duely obſerued: The eies of many beholde our actions: A ſpot is ſoone ſpied in our garments: A blemiſh quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly noted in our doings. It behooueth vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9567:11"/>to be carefull that our proceedings bee iuſt and honourable.</p>
            <p>But I muſt tell you one thing more, that in this laſt Acte of Parliament you haue brought me to a narowe ſtraight, that I muſt giue directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for her death, which cannot be to mee but a moſt grieuous and irkeſome burthen. And leaſt you might miſtake mine abſence from this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (which I had almoſt forgotten) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there be no cauſe why I ſhould willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come amongſt multitudes, for that amongeſt many ſome may be euil: yet hath it not bene the doubt of any ſuch daunger or occaſion that kept me from thence, but onely the great griefe to heare this cauſe ſpoken of, eſpecially, that ſuch a one of State and kin, ſhould neede ſo open a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, &amp; that this nation ſhould be ſo ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with blots of diſloialtie. Wherein the leſſe is my grief, for that I hope the better part is mine, and thoſe of the worſe not much to be accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, for that in ſeeking my deſtruction, they might haue ſpoiled their owne ſoules.</p>
            <p>And euen nowe coulde I tell you, that which woulde make you ſorie. It is a ſecrete, and yet I will tell it you, although it is knowen, I haue the propertie to keepe counſell, but too well often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to mine owne perill. It is not long ſince mine eyes did ſee it written, that an othe was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken within fewe daies, either to kill mee or to be hanged themſelues: &amp; that to be performed ere one moneth were ended. Hereby I ſee your dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:9567:11"/>in me, and neither can nor wil be ſo vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or careleſſe of your conſciences, as not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for your ſafetie.</p>
            <p>I am not vnmindeful of your oth made in the aſſociation, manifeſting your great goodwils &amp; affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s taken and entred into, vpon good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, &amp; true knowledge of the guilt, for ſafety of my perſon, &amp; conſeruation of my life: done (I proteſt to God) before I heard it, or euer thought of ſuch a matter, vntil a great nomber of handes with many Obligations were ſhewed mee, at Hampton Court, ſigned and ſubſcribed with the names and ſeales of the greateſt of this lande: which as I doe acknowledge as a perfect argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your true heartes, and great zeale to my ſafetie: ſo ſhall my bonde be ſtronger tied to greater care for all your good.</p>
            <p>But for as much as this matter is rare, waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and of great conſequence, I thinke you doe not looke for any preſent Reſolution: the rather, for that, as it is not my manner, in matters of far leſſe moment, to giue ſpeedy anſwer without due conſideration: ſo in this of ſuch importance, I thinke it verie requiſite with earneſt Prayer to beſeech his diuine Maieſtie, ſo to illuminate my vnderſtanding, and inſpire me with his grace, as I may doe and determine that, which ſhall ſerue to the eſtabliſhment of his Church, preſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your eſtates, and proſperitie of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth vnder my charge. Wherein (for that I knowe delaie is dangerous) you ſhal haue with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9567:12"/>all conueniencie our Reſolution deliuered by our meſſage. And what euer any Prince may merite of their Subiects, for their approoued te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of their vnfained ſinceritie, eyther by gouerning iuſtly, voide of all partialitie, or ſufferance of any iniuries done (euen to the pooreſt) that doe I aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly promiſe inuiolablie to performe, for requitall of your ſo many deſertes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:9567:12"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The occaſions of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond acceſſe.</head>
            <p>This Anſwere thus made by her Maieſtie, the Lords and Commons were diſmiſſed. And then her High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſome fewe dayes after, vpon deliberation had of this Petition, being (as it appeared) of her mercifull diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of nature, and her Princely magnanimitie, in ſome conflict with her ſelfe what to doe in a cauſe ſo weightie and important to her and the Realme, ſent by the Lorde Chauncelour (as I heard) and by the mouth of an Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſon, and a right worthy member of the lower houſe, this meſſage to both houſes: mouing and earneſtly charging them, to enter into a further conſideration, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there might not be ſome other way of remedy, then that they had already required, ſo farre diſagreeing from her owne naturall inclination. Whereupon, the Lords and Commons in either houſes aſſembled, had ſundry conſultations, both in their ſeuerall houſes generally, and by priuate Committees deputed ſpecially, and after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference had betwixt the ſayd Committees, it was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with vnanimitie of conſent amongſt them in the lower houſe, and by vniuerſall concorde in the vpper houſe, (the queſtion there propounded to euery one of the Lords) that there could be found no other ſound and aſſured meane, in the depth of their vnderſtanding, for the continuance of the Chriſtian religion, quiet of the Realme, and ſafetie of her Maieſties moſt Royall perſon, then that which was conteined in their former petition. The reaſons whereof, were ſummarily theſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe: which are more ſhortly reported, then they were vttered.</p>
            <div type="access_and_answer">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:9567:13"/>
               <head>A BRIEFE REPORT OF the ſecond acceſſe the 24. of Nouember 1586. and of the anſwere made in the name of the Lords of Parliament, to a meſſage ſent from hir MAIESTIE by the L. Chauncelour after hir firſt anſwere.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Lord Chauncelour accompanied with aboue fiue or ſixe and twentie Lords of Parliament, came before her Highnes in her Chamber of preſence, to deliuer the reſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all the Lords of Parliament, concerning a meſſage which he had not long before deliuered from her Maieſtie, for further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſultation, whether any other meanes could be thought of, or found out by any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, how the Scottiſh Queenes life might be ſpared, and yet her Maieſties perſon ſaued out of perill, and the ſtate of the Realme preſerued in quiet, declared, that according to that he had receiued in commandement from her Maieſtie, he had imparted the ſame to the Lordes aſſembled in the vpper houſe, whome he found by their generall ſilence much amazed at the propounding thereof, conſidering the ſame had bene before in deliberation amongſt them, and reſolued vpon, &amp; as appeared by their former petition exhibited to her Highneſſe, wherein they had expreſſed the ſame reſolution. Notwithſtanding, for her Maieſties further ſatiſfaction, they had entred into a newe conſultation, and for that purpoſe ſelected a great nomber of the choy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt perſons of that higher houſe of Parliament, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre thereof, either priuatly or together with the lower
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9567:13"/>houſe: which alſo was done accordingly at ſeueral times. At all which conferences it was concluded by them all, and ſo afterwards by the whole aſſembly of both houſes, that there could be no other aſſured meanes for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of her Maieſties life, &amp; continuance of Gods Religion, &amp; quiet of this State, then by the full execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſentence according to their former petition, inſtantly preſsing her Maieſtie with many arguments &amp; reaſons tending thereto, all which, though by diſtance from his Lordſhip I could not wel conceiue, yet this I did remember preciſely &amp; eſpecially was one, that as it were iniuſtice to denie execution of Law, at the ſuit of any one particular, and the meaneſt of her people: ſo much more, not to yeelde to the earneſt inſtance and humble prayers of all her faithful and louing ſubiects. And ſo concluded, with earneſt petition for her Maieſties reſolute determination and anſwere, for a preſent and ſpeedy direction by proclamation, and otherwiſe alſo, according to the forme of the ſtatute.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="summary_of_speech">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:9567:14"/>
            <head>A SVMMARIE REPORT of the ſecond ſpeech, vttered by the Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the Lower Houſe, by direction of all the Commons.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat if her Maiestie ſhould be ſafe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking away the life of the <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Queene,</hi> the ſame were moſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and probably to grow, by one of theſe meanes following.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1 Firſt,</hi> that happily ſhe might be reclaimed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>A repentant conuert,</hi> agniſing her Maieſties great mercie and fauours in remitting her heynous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and by her loyaltie hereafter, performe the fruites of ſuch conuerſion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> Or els, by a more <hi>Strayght guard</hi> be ſo kept, as there ſhoulde be no feare of the like attempts here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> Or, that good aſſurance might be giuen by <hi>Othe, Bonds</hi> or <hi>Hoſtages,</hi> as cautions for her good and loyal demeanour from henceforth.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Or laſtly, by <hi>Baniſhment,</hi> the realme might be voyded of her perſon, and thereby the perils further remoued, that growe to her Maieſtie by her preſence.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>The moments whereof being duely pondered, did yet appeare ſo light in all their iudgements, that they durſt not aduiſe any ſecuritie to reſt in any, no not in all of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For touching her <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſion,</hi> it was conſidered, that if pietie or duetie could haue reſtreined her fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9567:14"/>attempts, there was cauſe abundantly miniſtred to her on Maieſties behalfe, when ſhe not onely protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her againſt the viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of her own ſubiects, who pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued her to death by Iuſtice, but couered her honor, when the ſame by publique fame was touched, &amp; by very hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and capitall crymes obiected and proued againſt her before certeine Commiſſarie delegates aſsigned to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the ſame, more then blemiſhed, &amp; ſpared her lyfe, when for her former conſpiracies &amp; confederacies with the Northren Rebelles, her highneſſe was with great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance preſſed by both the houſes in the xiiii. yeere of her Maieſties reigne, to do like iuſtice vppon her, as nowe is deſired, and as her treaſonable practiſes then, had moſt iuſtly deſerued.</p>
            <p>And where the penaltie of this Acte ſufficiently notified vnto her, ſhould haue terrified her from ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked attempts, ſhe hath neuertheleſſe inſiſted in her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer practiſes, as a perſon obdurate in malice againſt her Maieſtie, and irrecouerable: ſo as there was no probable hope of any conuerſion, but rather great doubt and feare of relaps and recidiuation, foraſmuch as ſhe ſtood obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately in the deniall of matter moſt euidently prooued, and now moſt iuſtly ſentenced againſt her, and was not entred into the firſt part of repentance, <hi>The recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her offence,</hi> and ſo much the farther off from the true fruites that ſhould accompany the ſame.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>a ſurer guard,</hi> and more <hi>ſtrait impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> it was reſolued, that there was no ſecurity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, nor yet in the other two meanes propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of <hi>bonds</hi> and <hi>hoſtages:</hi> for aſmuch as the ſame meanes that ſhoulde bee practiſed to take her Maieſties life away
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:9567:15"/>(which God forbid) would aptly ſerue both for the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of her perſon, &amp; releaſe of the <hi>bonds</hi> &amp; <hi>hoſtages</hi> that ſhould be giuen for cautions in that behalfe: which being vnhappily atchieued, and to our irreparable loſse, who ſhoulde ſue the <hi>bonds,</hi> or deteine the <hi>hoſtages?</hi> or being deteined, what proportion was there in <hi>bonds</hi> or <hi>hoſtages</hi> whatſoeuer, to counteruaile the value of ſo precious and ineſtimable a Iewel, as her Maieſtie is to this Realme, and to vs all?</p>
            <p>But ſhe will ſolemnly vowe and take an othe, that ſhe will not attempt any thing to the hurt of her Maieſties perſon: Shee hath already ſundry times falſified her worde, her writing and her othe, and holdeth it for an article of religion, <hi>That faith is not to be holden with heretikes,</hi> of which ſort ſhee accompteth your Maieſtie, and all the profeſſors of the Goſpel to be: And therefore haue we litle reaſon to truſt her in that, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhee maketh ſo ſmall a conſcience.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>baniſhment,</hi> that were a ſtep <hi>à malo in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius</hi> to ſet her at libertie: a thing ſo greatly deſired and thirſted for by her adherents, and by ſome Princes her Allies, who ſought her enlargement chiefly, to make her a head to be ſet vp againſt her Maieſty, in time of inuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>To the which were added ſome fewe reaſons, collected out of her owne letters &amp; the confeſsion of <hi>Babington,</hi> her instrument and chiefe conſpiratour: by which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, howe her owne conſcience bewrayed what might iustly fal vpon her, in caſe any of her intended deſseigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments came to light: that ſhee might haply bee ſhut vp in ſome more cloſe and ſtraite priſon, as the <hi>Towre of London,</hi> if there befell her no worſe thing: and in that
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9567:15"/>ſhe directed <hi>Babington,</hi> in caſe he failed in the action of her deliuery, that he ſhould neuertheleſse proceede in the reſidue, which was the death of her Maiestie: who alſo confeſsed, that vpon aſsurance of her Maiesties death, or the arriuall of ſtrangers, he intended to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime of Q. of Scots, and made no doubt of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired ſucceſse: and therefore, her Maiesties death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo earnestly ſought, for aduancement of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitor, her Highnes could not remaine in quietnes or ſecuritie, if the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Queene ſhould longer continue her life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:9567:16"/>
            <head>THE SECOND ANSVVERE made by the Queenes Maieſtie, deliuered by her owne mouth, to the ſecond ſpeeche, vttered in the names of the Lords &amp; Commons of the Parliament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>VL <hi>grieuous is the way, whoſe going on and end, breede comber for the hire of a laborious iourney.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I haue</hi> ſtriued more this day then euer in my life, whether I ſhoulde ſpeake, or vſe ſilence. If I ſpeake and not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, I ſhal diſſemble: if I holde my peace, your labour taken were full vayne. For mee to make my mone, were ſtrange and rare: for I ſuppoſe you ſhal finde fewe, that for their owne particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, will comber you with ſuch a care. Yet ſuch I proteſt hath bene my greedy deſire and hungrie will, that of your conſultation might haue fallen out ſome other meanes to woorke my ſafetie ioyned with your aſſurance, (then that for which you are become ſuch earneſt ſutors) as I proteſt, I muſt needes vſe complaint, though not of you, but vnto you, and of the cauſe: for that I do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by your aduiſes, prayers, and deſires, there falleth out this accident, that <hi>Onely my Iniuerers bane, must be my lifes ſuertie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if any there liue ſo wicked of nature, to ſuppoſe, that I prolonged this time onely, <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forma,</hi> to the intent to make a ſhew of clemencie, thereby to ſet my prayſes to be wyer drawers to lengthen them the more: they doe me ſo great a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9567:16"/>wrong, as they can hardly recompence. Or if any perſon there be, that thinke or imagine, that the leaſt vayneglorious thought hath drawen mee further herein, they doe me as open iniurie as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was done to any liuing creature, as he that is the maker of all thoughtes, knoweth beſt to be true. Or if there bee any, that thinke, that the Lords appoynted in Commiſſion durſt do no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as fearing thereby to diſpleaſe, or els to be ſuſpected to be of a contrary opinion to my ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, they doe but heape vpon me iniurious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceites. For either thoſe put in truſt by me to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie my place, haue not haue ſignified vnto you all, that my deſire was, that euery one ſhould do according to his conſcience, &amp; in the courſe of his proceedings ſhould enioy both freedome of voyce &amp; libertie of opinion: &amp; what they would not onely declare, they might priuately to my ſelfe haue reuealed. It was of a willing minde &amp; great deſire I had, that ſome other means might be found out, wherein I ſhould haue taken more comfort, then in any other thing vnder the Sunne. And ſince nowe it is reſolued, that my ſuretie can not bee eſtabliſhed without a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe ende, I haue iuſt cauſe to complaine, that I, who haue in my time pardoned ſo many Rebels, winked at ſo many treaſons, and either not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced them, or altogether ſlipt them ouer with ſilence, ſhoulde nowe be forced to this procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, againſt ſuch a perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I haue beſides, during
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9567:17"/>my reigne, ſeene and heard many opprobrious bookes and Pamphlets againſt me, my Realme and State, accuſing me to be a Tyrant: I thanke them for their almes: I beleeue, therein their meaning was to tell me newes, and newes it is to me in deede: I would it were as ſtrange to heare of their impietie. What will they not now ſay, when it ſhalbe ſpread. That for the ſafety of her life, a Mayden Queene could be content to ſpill the blood, euen of her owne kinſewoman? I may therfore ful wel complaine, that any man ſhould thinke mee giuen to crueltie, whereof I am ſo guiltleſſe and innocent, as I ſhould ſlaunder God, if I ſhould ſay he gaue me ſo vile a minde: yea, I proteſt, I am ſo farre from it, that for mine owne life I would not touche her: neither hath my care bene ſo much bent howe to prolong mine, as how to preſerue both, which I am right ſory is made ſo hard, yea, ſo impoſſible.</p>
            <p>I am not ſo voide of iudgement, as not to ſee mine owne perill: nor yet ſo ignorant, as not to knowe it were in nature a fooliſh courſe, to cheriſh a ſworde to cutte mine owne throate: nor ſo careleſſe, as not to weigh that my life day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is in hazard: but this I do conſider, that many a man would put his life in daunger for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of a King, I doe not ſay that ſo will I: but I pray you thinke, that I haue thought vpon it.</p>
            <p>But ſith ſo many haue both written and ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt mee, I pray you giue me leaue to ſay ſomewhat for my ſelfe, and before you returne
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:9567:17"/>to your countries, let you know, for what a one you haue paſſed ſo careful thoughts. Wherin, as I thinke my ſelfe infinitely beholding vnto you al, that ſeeke to preſerue my life by al the meanes you may: ſo I proteſt vnto you, that there liueth no Prince, that euer ſhall be more mindefull to requite ſo good deſertes. And as I perceyue you haue kept your olde wonts, in a general ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the lengthning of my dayes: ſo am I ſure that I ſhall neuer requite it, vnles I had as many liues as you all: but for euer I will acknowledge it, while there is any breath left mee. Although I may not iuſtifie, but may iuſtly condemne my ſundry faults and ſinnes to God: yet for my care in this gouernment, let me acquaynt you with my intents.</p>
            <p>When firſt I tooke the Scepter, my title made me not forget the giuer: and therefore began, as it became me, with ſuch religion, as both I was borne in, bred in, &amp; I truſt ſhal die in. Although I was not ſo ſimple, as not to know what danger and perill ſo great an alteration might procure me: howe many great Princes of the contrary opinion woulde attempt all they might againſt me: and generally, what enimitie I ſhould breede vnto my ſelfe: which all I regarded not, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he, for whoſe ſake I did it, might, and would defend me. For which it is, that euer ſince I haue bene ſo daungerouſly proſecuted, as I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maruaile that I am, then muſe that I ſhould not be: if it were not Gods holy hand that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:9567:18"/>me, beyond all other expectation.</p>
            <p>Then entred I further into the ſchoole of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, bethinking what it fitted a King to do: and there I ſaw, he ſcant was wel furniſhed, if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he lacked Iuſtice, Temperance, Magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, or Iudgement. As for the two latter, I wil not boaſte, my ſexe doeth not permit it: But for the two firſt, this dare I ſay, Amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt my ſubiects I neuer knew a difference of perſon, where right was one: Nor neuer to my knowledge preferred for fauour, whome I thought not fit for worth: Nor bent my eares to credite a tale that firſt was tolde me: Nor was ſo raſh, to corrupt my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with my cenſure, before I heard the cauſe. I wil not ſay, but many reports might fortune be brought mee by ſuch as might heare the caſe, whoſe partialitie might marre ſometime the matter: For wee Princes may not heare all our ſelues. But this dare I boldly affirme, My verdit went euer with the trueth of my knowledge. As ful well wiſhed Alcibiades his friende, that hee ſhould not giue any anſwere, till he had recited the letters of the Alphabet: ſo haue I not vſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſudden reſolutions, in matters that haue touched me full neere: you wil ſay that with me, I thinke.</p>
            <p>And therfore, as touching your counſels and conſultations, I conceiue them to bee wiſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and conſcionable: ſo prouident and careful for the ſafetie of my life (which I wiſh no longer then may be for your good,) that though I neuer
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9567:18"/>can yeeld you of recompence your due: yet ſhall I endeuour my ſelfe to giue you cauſe, to thinke your good wil not ill beſtowed, &amp; ſtriue to make my ſelfe worthy for ſuch ſubiects.</p>
            <p>And now for your petition, I ſhal pray you for this preſent, to content your ſelues with an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere without anſwere: Your iudgement I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne not, neither do I miſtake your reaſons, but pray you to accept my thankfulneſſe, excuſe my doutefulneſſe, and take is good part my anſwere anſwereleſſe: wherein I attribute not ſo much to mine owne iudtgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but that I thinke many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s may go before me, though by my degree I go before them. Therefore if I ſhould ſay, I would not doe what you requeſt, it might peraduenture be more then I thought: and to ſay I would do it, might perhaps breed perill of that you labour to preſerue, being more then in your owne wiſdomes and diſcretions would ſeeme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of place and time being duely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:9567:19"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don by Chriſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes most excellent Maieſtie. 1586.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9567:19"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
